<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-02T20:40:40-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Chris Gardner | Web Developer</title><subtitle>I'm Chris Gardner, a former biomedical engineer, then photographer, now web developer. Ask me anything!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">And Now An Actual Update</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/16/and-now-an-actual-update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And Now An Actual Update" /><published>2020-03-16T01:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-16T01:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/16/and-now-an-actual-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/16/and-now-an-actual-update.html">&lt;p&gt;Now that the intro stuff is out of the way, here’s what I did today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Bootstrap is “mobile-first” I focused mainly on mobile styling, fiddling 
with buttons and stuff. I tried putting profile/login/signup links in a 
hamburger menu that only shows on mobile, but the default collapse animation
feels clunky, and I don’t like how it pushes the content down to make room for
the expanded menu. I could probably tinker with the animation, maybe remove it,
but that seems like a lot of work for what amounts to 4 buttons shown 2 at a
time at most (Profile/Logout and Login/Signup). I have a lot of ground to cover
before I can really start showing this off as a portfolio project, so I’m 
trying to avoid rabbit holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been taking design cues from the amazon mobile site for interacting with a
searchable database of items (well, recipes, but functionally similar just 
without cart+checkout). They use a hamburger/flip-out type menu, but I don’t
imagine I’d ever have as extensive a side-menu as Amazon, and I have some 
pretty strong opinions about UI and hiding things from the user (i.e. don’t do
it unless you really have to), so I think it’s best to just remove the 
hamburger and try to keep the buttons small enough to fit on the header. I also
have an image that brings you back to the home page, and I’d like to add one
more button for “Back to Search,” so I can’t justify a hamburger when there’s
enough space to fit everything without one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I am aware that my UI powers are held back by not using React or some
other modern frontend framework, but I’m still wrapping my head around the 
Rails backend stuff, so I’m keeping it vanilla Rails server-side-rendering for
now. I can always build a React frontend later (and I intend to).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>chris</name></author><summary type="html">Now that the intro stuff is out of the way, here’s what I did today:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Begin Hyperchef Log Alpha</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/16/begin-hyperchef-log-alpha.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Begin Hyperchef Log Alpha" /><published>2020-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/16/begin-hyperchef-log-alpha</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/16/begin-hyperchef-log-alpha.html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I guess it’s time I start blogging about this. I’ve been working on
Hyperchef (working title) for about a month now, in place of The Odin Project’s
Rails final project. They wanted me to replicate Facebook, mainly to get
experience with users and ActiveRecord associations. I wanted something
different though, something more useful to me than a fake social media site, so
I’m building a recipe site instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most advice on finding ideas is a some variant of “solve a problem you have
yourself,” and something I’ve encountered recently while trying to improve my
cooking skills is that all recipe sites are universally &lt;strong&gt;terrible&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I wanted was a recipe for Coq Au Vin to impress my wife, but after the 
fifth site in a row made me scroll through ten paragraphs on the author’s 
personal history of cooking to get to the actual instructions, I decided the
internet &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; in fact need one more recipe site. One that cuts out all the 
fluff, and maintains the shortest possible distance between “what do I want to
eat” and “here’s how to cook it.” No prose, no extended history of cheese
sauce, just meals with instructions. I also wanted to target people like me,
people who can turn on the oven and fry an egg, but don’t really know all the
ins and outs of cooking techniques, or how long a recipe &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; takes vs. 
how long the author thinks it takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hyperchef.herokuapp.com&quot;&gt;Hyperchef&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve probably already spent
more time on this than I would have on the final project, mainly due to the 
more complicated data models I’ve put together to support features that won’t
get built for some time. Instead of each recipe having a table of ingredients
with a little sprinkling of JS to change number of servings or from imperial to
metric units, everything lives in its own table in the database exactly once - 
even ingredients. Recipes are basically just a set of text steps and a bunch of
references to ingredients and what cookware is involved. Quantities of 
ingredients are saved on the join model between recipes and ingredients. I’m 
not sure if it’s actually more “efficient” than just writing a recipe on a page
and doing everything with JS, but I’m pretty proud of myself for putting it all
together. Once I add users and saving favorite recipes I’ll have covered 
everything the Odin Project wanted me to get out of the final project, but I’ll
probably keep going a bit further. I want to be able to take those favorite
recipes, add them to a weekly meal planner (or at least to a titled list), and
press a button to get a tabulated grocery list that sums all the ingredients
from all the recipes you picked for easy shopping. That’s the tool I want that
doesn’t exist, so once I can do all that I think I’ll be satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>chris</name></author><summary type="html">Well, I guess it’s time I start blogging about this. I’ve been working on Hyperchef (working title) for about a month now, in place of The Odin Project’s Rails final project. They wanted me to replicate Facebook, mainly to get experience with users and ActiveRecord associations. I wanted something different though, something more useful to me than a fake social media site, so I’m building a recipe site instead.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/15/first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Post" /><published>2020-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/15/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/15/first-post.html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it finally happened - I got a website! It may be a github.io site, but
it’s better than the big zip I had before. Most of the blog posts for a while
are going to be about the only Big Project I have right now,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hyperchef.herokuapp.com&quot;&gt;Hyperchef&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a recipe site, but you’ll
be hearing a lot more about it in the next several posts, so I hope you like
rambling thoughts on Rails app design!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what this blog will probably end up being: unsorted thoughts on current
projects, frustration at problems I’m stuck on, jubiliation when I’ve solved
them. Consider this less of a “10 quick tips for better coding” blog and more
of a “Holy wow I can’t believe I didn’t think of that…well it might’ve taken
two days but at least it’s fixed now” blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there might be pictures of my cats at some point, I haven’t decided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(but there probably will be)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>chris</name></author><summary type="html">Well, it finally happened - I got a website! It may be a github.io site, but it’s better than the big zip I had before. Most of the blog posts for a while are going to be about the only Big Project I have right now, Hyperchef. It’s a recipe site, but you’ll be hearing a lot more about it in the next several posts, so I hope you like rambling thoughts on Rails app design!</summary></entry></feed>